在这一节我想展示一下RSA加密如何在实际中应用的，尤其
In this segment I wanna show you how RSA
is used in practice and in particular, I
我想告诉你们有关一个叫做公钥加密技术头号PKCS的一个标准
wanna tell you about a standard called a
Public Key Cryptography standard number
我已经告诉你们很多次告诉大家你永远不应该
one PKCS one. So I've already told you a
couple of times that you should never use
用RSA加密密文，你也永远不能直接用RSA加密信息
what's called textbook RSA. You should
never directly encrypt the message using
因为它是不安全的。你在运用RSA 函数时总是对明文必须做点什么
RSA because that's insecure. You always
have to do something to the message before
我们在前一节了解了ISO标准
you actually apply the RSA function. We
saw the ISO standard in the previous
在这个标准中我们做的是生成随机值x，用RSA对x进行加密
segment where what we did is we generated
a random x, encrypted x using RSA, and
之后从x我们可以派生一个对称加密密钥，但是实际这不是RSA在实际中的应用
then from this x we derived a symmetric
encryption key. But that's actually not how
在实践中有所不同和典型
RSA is used in practice. In practice
things worked a little differently and
是指系统生成加密密钥，之后
typically what happens is the system
generates a symmetric encryption key and
RSA与其被用于加密这个给出的对称加密密钥
then RSA is asked to encrypt the given
symmetric encryption key rather than
不如用于生成对称密钥作为我们同一加密法或者RSA加密的一部分，
generating the symmetric key as part of
[our same encryption or RSA encryption?]. So in practice as I
所以说，RSA体系是指给出这个输入一个对称加密密钥，
say, what happens the RSA system is given
this input a symmetric encryption key to
例如，这里有个a是AES密钥，128长度的比特串
encrypt for example this could be a, an AES
key that would be like 128 bits and then
之后实际加密的方法是首先我们把这128个比特串
the way this key is actually encrypted is
first we take these 128 bits and we expand
扩大为全模尺寸。例如，2048个比特串
them into the full modulo size. For
example, this would be 2048 bits, and then
之后我们再用RSA函数。那么问题是，这个预处理怎么做呢？
we apply the RSA function. And so the
question is, how should this preprocessing
给出的这128个比特串怎么扩大乘2048个比特值以应用于RSA呢？
be done? How should we expand the 128 bit
AES key that was given to us into a 2048
并且进一步的一个问题是
bit value that can then be applied with
RSA. And then furthermore the question is,
我们又怎么讨论这个结果体系是安全的呢？所有解决
how do we argue that the resulting system
is secure? So in all the way of doing it
这些问题的方法是在实践中被广泛使用的称作PKCS1.5版本
which is actually very widely deployed in
practice is what's called PKCS1 version
即公钥加密标准，即PKCS的含义
1.5, Public Key Cryptography Standard,
that's what PKCS stands for. So I wanna
我想给你们看一下这个机制是怎么工作的，尤其说一下什么叫做
show you how this mechanism works and in
particular, I'll show you what's called
PKCS模式2，模式2代表加密，模式1代表数字签字
PKCS1 Mode 2. Mode 2 denotes
encryption, mode 1 denotes signatures so
所以这里我们将关注这个加密方法。PKSC1工作如下
here we're gonna just focus on the
encryption. So the way PKCS1 works is
你拿到你的明文，例如，这是128比特的AES密钥
as follows, you take your message, this
would be the 128 bit AES key for example,
你把它当做最低有效位输入
and you put it as a least significant bit
of the value that you're creating. The
接下来，你应该做的是给它添加16个比特，
next thing you do is you append sixteen
bits of one to it, you know [foreign].
这里是16个比特，之后你做的是添加这随机的填补位
This is sixteen bits of one. And then the
next you do is you append the random pad
在这个随机填补位的任何一处都不包含FF。
that actually does not contain FF
anywhere inside the random pad. So this
所以这实际上它有些像它的序列，1900个随机比特
is basically something like on the order
of what is it, 1900 random bits except
除了在这些随机比特字中的FF序列。最后，在最顶端
that there are on FF's inside those random
bits and finally at the very top, you put
放置数字02，这说明这个明文已经用PKSC1模式2加密了
the number 02. This indicates that this
plain text has been encoded using PKCS1
这里的所有值，我们生成的所有值
mode 2. And then this whole value here,
this whole thing that we just created.
这仅仅的2048个比特串被送入RSA函数
This is just 2048 bit string is the thing
that gets fed into the RSA function and is
之后被升为e的次方模n。输出结果是PKCS1密文
raised to the power of e modulo N. And the
resulting thing is PKCS1 ciphertext. Now
这个解密方法是倒置RSA函数，将会返回这个模块
the decrypter of course is going to invert
the RSA function, He's gonna get back this
看一下这个最高有效位，它将说
block, He's gonna look at the most
significant bits and he's gonna say
这里有一个02，这意味着PKCS1格式化了，因为它是PKCS1的格式化
there's a 02 in there that means that this
PKCS one formatted. Since it's PKCS one
所以他将移动这些02.之后将移动这所有的填补直达FF
formatted, it's gonna remove those 02.
It's gonna remove all the random pad up
凡落后的事物都是之后将要用到的原始信息，
until the FF. And then anything
that stays beyond that is the original
并且你知道解密这密文的实际内容
message which is then used you know to say
decrypt the actual body of the ciphertext.
正如我说的这种机制被相当广泛的使用了，例如
And as I said, this mechanism is extremely
widely deployed, For example, it's used in
被用于HTTPS中，有意思的是，这个PKCS1 1.5版本在80年代后期设计出来的
HTTPS. Now interestingly, this PKCS1
version 1.5 was designed in the late 80's.
的确没有安全证据来说明这个机制是安全的
There was really no security proof to
argue that this mechanism is in fact
当没有安全证据时，事物是易被攻破证明是普遍存在的
secure. And as it turns out, it is very
common when there is no security proof, it
并且存在一个非常非常高端的攻击
turns out that actually things break and
there's a very, very elegant attack due to
由于1998年Bleichenbacher的返回，丹尼尔Bleichenbacher向我们
Bleichenbacher back in 1998, Daniel
Bleichenbacher which shows how to attack
展示了如何攻击PKCS1，当它被用于HTTPS里面时。所以让我们看一下这个攻击如何展开的
PKCS1 when it's used for example inside of
HTTPS. So let's see how the attack works.
这个思路是，假设攻击者拦截了一个确定的密文
So the idea is this, supposed the attacker
intercepted a certain ciphertext so this
就是PKCS1密文，那么关键是它用PKCS1编码的，之后
is PKCS1 ciphertext so the point is
it's encoded using PKCS1 and then the
结果被送入RSA函数，我们称这密文是RSA函数的输出
result is fed into the RSA function. And
we call the ciphertext the output of the
攻击者想破解这个密文，
RSA function. The attacker wants to
basically decrypt the ciphertext, So let
那么让我给大家详细展示一下这攻击者是怎么做的。我们仅仅简化一下SSL
me show you abstractly what the attacker
is gonna do. We're gonna just simplify SSL
并且这个攻击者实际上可以直接把密文发送到网络服务器
and just say that the attacker can
basically send the ciphertext directly to
网络服务器将尝试用它的密钥破解这个密文
the web server. The web server is gonna
try and decrypt the ciphertext using its
之后他会成功吗？在加密之后他做的第一件事是
secret key. And then what is it gonna do?
Well, the first thing it does after the
将会问对破解的密文是用PKCS1编码的吗？
encryption, well, it's gonna ask: is the
decryption of the ciphertext PKCS1
换句话说，看到这最高有效位会问
encoded? In other words, it's gonna look
at the most significant bits and ask: is
在这最高有效位是02吗？如果是，将继续
this 02 in the most significant positions? If
they are, it's gonna continue properly
正确地解密并继续使用这个协议，如果这些位置不是02
decrypting and then continue with the
protocol and if there is no 02 in those
将会警告一个错误执行，所以，如果这明文的最高有效位是
positions, it's gonna announce an error.
So if the most significant bits of the
02，将如期继续这个协议，如果最高有效位
plaintext are 02, it's gonna continue
with the protocol as expected, if the most
不是02将会返回一个错误信息并告诉攻击者
significant bits are not 02 is gonna send
back an error message and tell the
输入了无效的密文。现在不可思议的是
attacker, hey, you sent in invalid
ciphertext. Now the amazing thing is that,
这会让要求攻击者测试给出的密文中解密最显著
this lets the attacker test whether the
sixteen most significant bits of the
的16位比特数是否是02.换句话说，就是
decryption of the given ciphertext are 02
or not. In other words, the attacker can
攻击者可以提交任何他想提交的密文给web服务。web服务将会
submit whatever ciphertext he wants to the
web server. The web server will invert the
转化RSA公钥加密算法，之后告诉攻击者转化后是否从02
RSA function and then tell the attacker
whether the inversion started with 02 or
开始。所以在某种意义上说是给攻击者一个提示让他检测
not. So in some sense gives the attacker an
oracle that lets him test whether the
密文的转换是不是从02开始的。这也证明了
inversion of any ciphertext begins with 02
or not. And it turns out that's actually
实际上解密攻击者所期望的密文是完全可行的。只要加上一点点因为
enough to completely decrypt any
ciphertext the attacker wants, Just add
RSA公钥加密算法的信息泄露，攻击者至少
little bit of information leakage just by
properties of RSA lest the attacker
可以完全的解密一个给定的密文。所以这就是攻击者想做的。
completely decrypt a given ciphertext.
Also here's what the attacker is gonna do,
如果他有一个想解密的密文，他要做的就是将这个得到的密文
well, he has a ciphertext that he wants to
decrypt so what he'll do is he'll take a
直接输入web服务并且询问
cyphertext and of course feed that
directly into the web server and ask does
它是否是从02开始的。他要做的下一步就是选择一个
it begin with the 02 or not. The next
thing he's gonna do is he's gonna chose a
随机值R然后建立一个新的密文c集合。它也就是
random value r and he's gonna build a new
ciphertext c prime. Which is (r to the e)
c模N。现在要做什么呢？如果我们吧r带入RSA函数中
c modulo N. Now what does that do? If we
pull the r into the RSA function, really
那我们做的就是我们乘了rsa的密文。你知道数据包1
what we just did is we multiply the RSA
plaintext, you know the PKCS1 including
中包含了m，我们让r和m相乘，这个样子我们最终得到的是r的e次方。
in m, we multiply that by r and that,
that whole thing gets raised to the power
好了，这就是将c与（r的e次方)相乘得到的。它使密文和
of e. Okay. So that's the effect of
multiplying c by (r to the e). It multiplies
r相乘，一个被攻击者控制的值。之后攻击者
the plaintext by r, a value that the
attacker controls. And then he's gonna
会把c一撇输入web服务中，web服务会承认这次会话，然后以02或者
send c prime to the web server and the web
server is gonna say yes, this starts with
不是02开始.所以现在我们可以概括一下这个问题
02 or no, this doesn't start with 02. So
now we can abstract this problem to
把这个问题简化成更平常的你可以想象的问题，就比如我的脑中有一个
something more general which you can think
of as the following so I have this number
未知数x。这个数是我尝试编码m从数据包1中得到的。我在考虑
x in my head. This is the number I'm
trying to get The PKCS1 encoding on m. I'm
这个未知数x，之后我想让你们做的事情是对r做的。针对你选择的r我要告诉你们的是
thinking of this number x and then what I
let you do is for r, which way r of your
r倍的x模n是否从02开始。同时这也证明了
choice I will tell you whether r times x mod n
starts with 02 or not. And it turns out by
询问足够的问题，事实证明不是很多这种类型的问题，
asking enough questions it turns out
either by million questions of this type,
你可以回复所有的未知数x。通过学习利用询问方式找到r倍的x
you can basically recover all of x. Just
by learning whether r times x begins with 02
是否从02开始，你确实可以复原x。所以在现实中
or not by asking enough questions, you can
actually recover x. So in reality what
这意味着攻击者可以获取一个给定的密文。可能
this means is that the attacker can
capture a given ciphertext. This maybe
对应着用户使用信用卡的编号或者是
corresponds to a ciphertext where the user
enters the credit card number or a
密码，现在攻击者想解密这个密文。他要做的事
password, and now the attacker wants to
decrypt the ciphertext. What he would do
是发送百万级的像这样的密文，web服务会回复每个
is he would send about a million
ciphertext like this, the web server for
密文是否以02开始或者不是，在这个攻击的结尾
each ciphertext is gonna respond whether
the plaintext begins with 02 or not and at
攻击者就会以块分割它们，也就是密文c
the end of the attack, the attacker just
blocks away with the, decryption of the
的译码。所以这对你来说可能有一点魔术意味，你能从仅仅是
ciphertext c. So this might seem a
little magical to you, how are you able to
特征比特是不是02知道什么呢，你怎么样
just from learning whether the most
significant bits are 02 or not, how you're
去还原全部的简单密钥。所以让我为你展示一个简单地例子。
able to recover the entire plain text. So
let me show you a simple example of this.
我将会把那些基本攻击加值叫做Bleichenbacher仅仅是为了让大家稍微了解一下
I'll call those bab y Bleichenbacher just
to kinda get the idea across on how this
这样的攻击可能怎么工作。想象一下攻击者有能力发送密文c，
attack might work. So imagine that the
attacker is able to send the ciphertext c,
web服务将会使用秘密密钥去解密但是让我们假设
the web server is gonna use the secret key
to decrypt but let's suppose that instead
它可能会替对02的检查也可能不会，所有的web服务所做的就是攻击者
of checking for 02 or not, all the web
server does is he asked is the most
所询问的特征比特1或是0 如果特征比特是1，那么web服务会
significant bit one or not. If the most
significant bit is one, the web server
回到是的，如果特征比特不是1，那么web服务就会拒绝。更深一侧，
says yes. If the most significant bit is
not one, the web server is no. Moreover,
为了简化问题，我们假设RSA加密模块是2的n次方，也就是说
to simplify things, let's assume that the
RSA module is n is a power of two. So n =
n=2^n。当然，这并不是一个有效的RSA解码。RSA解码通常是
two^n. Of course, this is not a valid RSA
modulus. An RSA modulus used to be a
两个不同的集合的产物。但是为了让事情变得简单一点，
product of two distinct primes. But again,
just to keep things simple, let's pretend
我们假设存在这一时刻n确实是2^N，所以你们现在知道了通过
for a second that n is actually a power of
two. So now you realize that by sending
发送密文c到web服务，敌手就会得到特征
the ciphertext c over to the web server,
the adversary just learn the most
比特的明文x。事实上，服务的行为完全
significant bits of the plaintext x.
Basically, the servers behavior completely
显示了特征比特，现在攻击者需要做的就是
reveals what the most significant is. Now
what the attacker can do is he can
把密文乘上e的二次方。现在乘上e的二次方
multiply the ciphertext by two to the e.
Now multiplying by two to the e has the
对于密文来说就相当于2倍x的e。次方
effect of multiplying the plaintext x. By
two simply multiplying x by two and
并且，因为我们要求2x的模n，也就是左边这个式子。
because we're working mod two to the N,
multiplying by two basically means shift
好的，所以事实上现在当我们左进位我们就会知道2x的特征
left, okay. So now when we shift left in
fact we get to learn the most significant
比特，也就是x的第二特征比特。好的，我们把x左进位后
bits of 2x which is really the second most
significant bit of x, okay. So, again the
就得到了2x的特征比特。我们分解解密
most significant bit of 2x basically we
shift x to the left. And we reduce modulo
n。所以现在2x的特征比特模n实际上就是x的其次
n. So now, the most significant bit of 2x
modulo n is basically the second most
特征比特。所以现在我们知道了另一个x的字符。我们现在开始
significant bit of x. So now we learned
another bit of x. And now we're gonna
重复上面的步奏。我们会开始质疑4的e次方乘c，这和质疑
repeat this again. We're gonna query a
four to the e  c, That corresponds to
4x的e次方是一致的。针对4x的询问实际上也反映了4x特征
querying of 4x to the power e. Querying of
4x basically reveals the most significant
比特。这就反映了俩比特进位。也就意味着，我们
bit of 4x mod n. 4x  four corresponds the
shifting by two bits. Which mean now we
现在早知道了x的第三特征比特。当我们重复再重复，
get to learn the third most significant
bit of x. And when we repeat this again,
之后得到了不同的c的明文。你可以看到很少的几个讯问后，大约1000或者
and again, and again for different multip
les of c and you can see that after just a
2000个询问，我们就能复原全部的x。之所以Bleichenbacher
few queries, about a 1,000 or 2,000
queries, we'll recover all of x. The
需要百万级的询问的原因是没有测试
reason Bleichenbacher needed about a
million queries is because he wasn't
第一次，实际上就是是否针对是02进行测试。所以他需要
testing for one, He was actually testing
for 02 or not 02 and that basically means
百万级的询问而不是2000次的，但是无论如何
that he needs instead of 2,000 queries he
needs actually a million queries but
依旧足够去复原所有的密文。
that's still enough to recover all of the
plaintext text. Okay? So I hope this is
我希望这能解释这个攻击为什么是可能的 为什么这一点关于
explains why this attack is possible. Why
just this little bit of information about
RSA反转中最重要的比特的信息就足以完全破解RSA
the most significant bits of the RSA
inverse is enough to completely decrypt
这里的底线是像上面那样被用于网络服务器的PACK1
RSA. So the bottom line here is that PKCS1 as implemented in web server as up
在这个攻击被发现之前基本上是安全的
until this attack was discovered was
basically insecure because the attacker
因为攻击者可以通过向网络服务器发送足够的查询就能破解密文
could essentially decrypt a ciphertext he
wants just by issuing enough queries to
所以 我们要怎样来抵御这种攻击呢
the web server. So how do we defend
against this attack? Well, so the SSL
SSL团体的想要减少他们代码的变化这样就能避免
community basically wanted the minimum
change in their code that would prevent
有效攻击 如果你注意到RFC 他们所提出的是
this attack from working and so if you
look at the RFC, what they propose is the
好吧 这里有很多的文字 他们所提出的就是
following. Well, there's a lot of text
here but basically what they propose is to
如果在你使用了RSA解密之后 你收到一个不是PACK1编码的明文
say that if after you apply the RSA
decryption, you get a plaintext that's not
换句话说就是它不是以02开头的 那么你应该做的就是
PKCS1 encoded. In other words it doesn't
start with 02. What you're supposed to do
随机选择一个字符串R  然后只用假装这个明文
is basically choose some random string r.
And just pretend that the plaintext is
只是一个随机的字符串R 然后当做什么都没发生一样继续 当然
just a random string r and continuous as
nothing happened and of course the
协议之后会失效 具体来说就是 如果PACK1编码是错误的
protocol will fail later on. So to be
concrete you see if the PKCK1 encoding
你要做的就是 声称预制密钥就是这个
is not correct, what you would do is you
would just say the premaster secret is
随机字符串 然后继续协议
this random string or that we just picked
up off thin air and let's continue the
当然建立的会话会失败因为客户端和服务器
protocol and of course the session set up
will fail because the client and the
会认同不同的密钥这样就导致会话终止
server will end up agreeing on different
keys and that will cause the session to
所以实际上我们并没有告诉攻击者明文是不是以02开头的
terminate. So we actually don't tell the
attacker whether the plaintext begins with
我们所做的就是假装明文是一些随机的数值
02 or not. All we do is just pretend that
the plaintext is some random value. So
对于网络服务器来说这只是细微的代码变化 而且它是容易实施的
this was a minor code change to many web
servers and it was fairly easy to get
实际上 如今大部分网络服务器使用这个版本的PACK1
deployed and in fact most web servers out
there today implement this version of
然而 这就引发了PACK1是否应该被
PKCS1. However, this kind of raises the
question of whether PKCS1 should be
完全改变从而我们能够证明它具有选择密文安全性
changed all together so that we actually
are able to prove chosen ciphertext
这就给了我们另外一种使用RSA加密的方式
security. And that brings us to a
different way of doing encryption using
这种方式被称为最优非对称加密填充 简称OAEP 事实上
RSA which is called Optimal Asymmetric
Encryption Padding, OAEP. And in fact the
PKCS标准被更新 而且2.0版本的PKCS1实际上是支持OAEP的
PKCS standard was updated and PKCS1 version
2.0 actually has support for OAEP which is
而OAEP是一种RSA加密的更好方式 所以让我来解释下OAEP是如何工作的
a better way of doing RSA encryption. So
let me explain how OAEP works. So OAEP is
OAEP是94年BEllare和Rogaway发明的 OAEP的运行方式如下
due to the Bellare and Rogaway back in 1994. And
the way OAEP works is as follows. So you
选取一个你想要加密的信息 比如这个128比特的AES密钥
take your message that you wanna encrypt
this for example could be the 128 bits AES
然后 首先要做的就是给它附加上一段短填充
key. And then the first thing you do is
you append a short pad to it. So in this
在这种情况下 将01加到开始的位置然后再加一堆0
case, you put a 01 in the beginning and
then you add a whole bunch of zeroes. How
至于多少0取决于标准 但是你们知道这里应该有128个0
many zeroes is actually depends on the
standard but you know that's supposed like
同时选取一个随机的数值
they're 128 zeroes in here. And then you
also choose a random value so that this
让整个字符串和RSA的模数一样大 比如2047比特
whole string is as big as your RSA modulus
so let's just say this is 2047 bits. Now
在你使用RSA函数之前 首先要把你选择的随机数值
before you apply the RSA function, you
first of all take the random value that
输入到哈希函数中 哈希函数会产生一个
you chose and you feed it into the hash
function. This hash function produces a
和左侧编码一样大的数值 把输出进行异或
value that's as big as the left hand side
of your encoding. You XOR the outputs.
将得到的结果输入到另外一个被称为G哈希函数中
You feed the result into another hash
function which we call g. You XOR
将结果和随机数值进行异或 最后 就得到了两个被连接在一起的数值
that with a random value. And then
finally, you get these two values that you
不管连接的是左侧
concatenate together. Okay, So, you
concatenate either left side and the
还是右侧 都将得到2047比特的长度
right side that gives you something that
says is 2047 bits long and that's the thing
并把它输入到RSA函数上 得到的输出就是RSA的加密
that you apply the RSA function to. And the
result is the RSA encryption. Now there's
这里有一个在2001年被Fujisaki Okamoto Pointcheval 和Stern证明的理论
a theory that was proved in 2001, due to
Fujisaki, Okamoto, Pointcheval, and Stern,
它将向你证明如果你所做的是将RSA函数假定为一个陷门置换
that shows that in fact if all you do is
you, you assume that the RSA function is a
一个安全的置换操作 但实际上这种用RS加密的模式
Trapdoor permutation, a secure Trapdoor
permut ation, but in fact this mode of
实际上是选择密文安全的 但是
encrypting using RSA is in fact chosen
ciphertext secure but we have to
我们必须假设函数H和G都是理想的哈希函数 正如我所说
assume that the functions h and g are kind
of ideal hash functions as I said these
它们被称为随机oracle 我们假设H和G就是
are called random oracles. Basically, we
assume that h and g are just random
从定义域映射到值域的随机函数 在实际运用中
functions from their domains to their
range. In practice of course when OAEP is
当使用OAEP时 人们只对H和G使用SHA-256 这为什么被称为
implemented, people just use SHA-256
say for h and g. Why is this called
最优非对称加密填充 为什么是这个o 为什么这表示最佳
Optimal Asymmetric Encryption Padding?
Why is this o? Why does this stands for
原因是如果你观察密文 就会注意到
optimal? Well, the reason is if you look
at the ciphertext, you'll notice that the
密文基本上达到它所能达到的最短 密文正好是一个RSA输出的长度
ciphertext is basically as short as it can
be. The ciphertext is exactly the length
这里没有附加在密文上的尾部的数值
of one RSA output, there are no trailing
values that are appended to the ciphertext
比如在ISO标准中 如果你记得 即便你要加密一个很短的信息
whereas for example, the ISO standard
if you remember even if you had to encrypt
你要做的就是将x用RS加密
a very short message, what you would have
to do is you would have to encrypt x using
然后将它附加到x上 这就是在对称加密系统下对短信息的加密
RSA and then append to that x, the
encryption with the short message under
即便你只用加密一个128比特长度的AES密钥
the symmetric encryption system. So even
if you have just to encrypt a 128 bit AES
通过ISO标准你就会德奥一个RSA输出并附加一个对称的密码
key, with the ISO standard you would
get one RSA output plus a symmetric
而在OAEP中 你只会得到一个RSA输出 所以在这种情况下
cipher whereas with OAEP, you just get one
RSA output and nothing else so in that
它是最优的 最优在于密文的长度
sense, it's optimal, Optimal in terms of
the length of the ciphertext.
有趣的是 这种理论十分依赖于RS的特性 实际上
Interestingly, this theorem here really
rely on properties of RSA. And in fact,
如果你使用一个普通的陷门置换的话 这种理论就是错误的
the theorem is known to be false if
you use a general trapdoor permutation.
其他的一些置换并不具备RSA的代数特性
Some other permutation doesn't have the
algebraic properties of RSA. So that left
这就遗留下了问题 如果我们有一个普通的陷门置换 什么才是使用OAEP的正确方式
this question of if we have a general
trapdoor permutation, what is the correct
结果对于OAEP有小的修正
way to do OAEP? And it turns out, there's
a minor modification to OAEP which makes
这样结果更具普适性 这是在2001年返回Shoup导致的
the result more general. This is a result
due to Shoup back in 2001. Just shows that
来看看如果给一个普通的陷门置换f会有什么情况
if you give me a general trapdoor
permutation f. It turns out if you replace
结果表明替换掉通过哈希函数使用OAEP的固定填充 这个哈希函数
the fixed pad that's using OAEP by a hash
function, this hash function w, which
恰巧就是消息m和加密所用的随机性r的哈希函数
happens to be a hash function of the
message m and the randomness r that
解密时要确保哈希函数值是对的
you're encrypting with, and then during
decryption, you actually check that this
解密时还要确保变量m和r对应函数值w
hash function value is correct. So when
you decrypt, you actually check the w of
写入了明文的位置
mr is really what's written in this
position in the plaintext. If you do that
如果是这样的话这样的OAEP基本上就是OAEP+
then basically this OAEP called OAEP+.
Is in fact CCS secure, Chosen Ciphertext
事实上这就是任何陷门置换的CCS安全性（被选密文安全）
Secure for any trapdoor permutation. You
don't have to rely on a specific
安全不需要依靠RSA的特性 还会产生另一个结果简单非对称加密填充
properties of RSA. There's another result
called Simple Asymmetric Encryption
SAEP+是说如果要利用RSA的特性
Padding, SAEP+ which basically says
that if you are gonna rely on properties
当公共指数3用RSA这种特定方式
of RSA, then in particular way with RSA
when the public exponent is equal to
事实上不需要进行第二阶段的加密
3, it turns out you actually don't
need the second stage of encryption. The
又一次使用函数w的简单填充模式
simple padding scheme here again using the
function w is actually already enough to
足够保证被选密文安全性
guarantee chosen ciphertext security. So
these are variants OAEP but they're not
所以有很多种OAEP但不是都被使用 我只是提出来让你们了解它们的存在
really used. I just wanted to mention and
to let you know they exist. These are not
主要是标准OAEP被使用
really used mainly OAEP has been
standardized is what's used. Although
RSA在公共加密最广泛的应用
again in reality, the most common
application of RSA for public encryption
事实上是HTTPS REF标准化的PKCS1
is in fact this PKCS1 that's
standardized in the HTTPS RFC. So just to
你要清楚实际如何进行解密
make sure it is clear in your mind how
decryption actually works, let me ask you,
我来问你怎么解密SAEP密文
how would you decrypt an SAEP ciphertext
ct. So here, you're given the ciphertext
密文给定是ct 在于这三个理论哪个是适用于解密
ct here and the question is which of these
three methods is the correct way of
是第一个 我们来看看为什么
decrypting the ciphertext. So the correct
answer is the first one and let's see why.
密文给定 我们首先要用RSA取反函数
Well, given the ciphertext the first thing
what we need to do is apply the RSA
我们能通过密文得到在x和r情形下RSA明文
inverse functions, the ciphertext and that
will give us the RSA plaintext which
所以要给出x和r
happens to be in this case x and r. So we
get this x and r here. The next thing we
然后我们需要带入哈希函数得到r 和结果异或
need to do is we need to hash r using the
function h and XOR the result with x and
就能得到m和w(m,r) 最后我们要保证填充W(m,r)是正确的
that will give us m and wm, r. And the
last we need to do is to make sure that
验算w是否等于W(m,r)
the pad W(m,r) is correct so we check that
in fact w is equal to W(m,r) and if so we
如果等就输出m 如果不等输出bottom说明密文无效
output m and if not, we output bottom to
say that the ciphertext is invalid and
解密算法丢弃它
the decryption algorithm rejects it. And
by the way I'd like to emphasize that this
顺便强调一下加密填充过程的核算在所以我们所见过的机制中都是很重要的
checking of the pad during decryption is
crucial in all of the schemes that we
例如在OAEP+和SAEP+中进行解密
just saw. So for example, in both OAEP+ and SAEP+, it's doing decryption.
确保正确填充很重要
It's very important to check that the pad
is in fact correct so that the value of w
我们用来加密的w值 就是m和r待人哈希函数得到的值
that you get here during the encryption
really is the hash under the capital W of
类似的对于OAEP 在解密过程中核算很重要
m and r and similarly on OAEP, it's very
important to check it during decryption.
事实上填充值是不变的010000000
In fact, the value of the pad is the
constant 010000000. And of course if it
当然如果不是01000就输出bottom 宣告密文无效
happens to be not 01000 then you output
bottom and you say the ciphertext is
最后我想指出执行OAEP是是否聪明的做法
invalid. The last thing I wanna point out
is that actually implementing OAEP can be
我们来看看为什么这样说 假设你编写一个OAEP解密程序
quite tricky and let's see why. So
supposed you have, you write an OAEP
用密文作为输入
decryption routine that takes the
ciphertext as input. The first thing you
首先对密文使用RSA取反函数
would do is you would apply the RSA
inverse function to the ciphertext and you
想得到n比特值输出
would say well, you expect to get an n bit
value out, you know 2047 bits in the case
已经知道在2048比特RSA模函数的2047比特
of 2048 bit RSA modulus and if you get
something that's bigger than two to the
如果有比2047的2次方大的数 声称丢弃
2047, you say reject. We say error = one
and we go to Exit. The next thing we're
声称错误为1 退出
gonna do is we're gonna check whether the
pad is in fact the correct pad and again
然后要核查这个填充是否正确 然后再一次拒绝并退出
if the pad is not the correct pad, then
again, we're gonna reject and go to Exit.
这个执行的问题在于 应该意识到即使现在对于定时攻击来说
The problem with this implementation is
well by now I hope you kind of guessed it
这样的加密是脆弱的
is it's vulnerable to a timing attack,
right. So essentially by leaking timing
因此通过定时信息的泄露攻击者很容易计算出哪出错
information the attacker can now figure
out what caused the error. Was it, that
是因为RSA解密很复杂出现错误
was there an error the RSA decryption
happened to be too big or was there an
或者由于填充太多出现错误
error because the pad happened to be too
large? And if the attacker can this
如果攻击者能通过定时区分这两种错误
distinguish these two errors say by
timing. Then it turns out similar to the
如果和Bleichenbacher攻击很像 很可能完全解出你选择的任何密文
Bleichenbacher attack, it's possible to
completely decrypt any ciphertext of your
即便是非常非常小的信息泄露
choice. Just at very, very, very small
leak of information would completely allow
也可以让攻击解密出他想要的所用密文
the attacker to decrypt completely any
ciphertext that he wants to. So this shows
其实正确执行了OAEP的数学理论
that if you, even if you implement the
mathematics of OAEP decryption correctly,
也非常容易弄砸很容易自己暴露在定时的攻击下
you can very easily mess up and open
yourself up to a timing attack which would
执行就非常不安全
make your implementation completely
insecure. So as usual, the lesson is,
依照以往的经验就是不要自己加密
don't implement crypto yourself in
particular, RSA OAEP is particularly
对于自己执行来说RSA OAEP真的很危险 例如使用标准函数库
dangerous to implement yourself. Just use one
of the standard libraries for example,
OpenSSL有OAEP执行功能
OpenSSL has an OAEP implementation and of
course what they do is very careful to
当然它会非常小心地保证OAEP解密时间总是相同
make sure that the running time of OAEP
decrypt is always the same no matter what
不管出现了什么错误 这节到此结束
causes the error. Okay, So let's stop here
and then in the next segment we'll talk
下节将介绍RSA陷门置换的安全性
about the security of the RSA trapdoor
permutation.